Guide to the Emma Octavia Lundberg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Emma Octavia Lundberg Papers,
1834-1971
Lundberg, Emma Octavia, 1881-1954.
4 linear feet (9 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0809
4079053
This collection contains research files, speeches, writings and other material related to Emma O. Lundberg, a child welfare leader who served the Wisconsin Industrial Commission, the United States Children's Bureau, the Child Welfare League of America, and the New York Temporary Emergency Relief Administration. Throughout her nearly forty-year career in social work, Lundberg wrote extensively about child welfare; most of the papers relate to her writings and research.
Biographical Note
Emma Octavia Lundberg, child welfare leader, was born in Västergötland, Sweden on October 8, 1881, to Frans Vilhelm Lundberg and Anna Kajsa Johanson. The family emigrated from Sweden in 1884, and Lundberg spent her childhood in Rockford, Illinois, graduating from Rockford High School in 1901. Two years later Lundberg entered the University of Wisconsin at Madison, earning her B.A. in 1907 and a master's degree in 1908.
From 1908 to 1913, Lundberg worked in several cities studying living-standards and immigrant households, and engaged in family welfare work. Among the organizations that Lundberg worked for were the United States Immigration Commission, the United Charities of Chicago, the Associated Charities in Madison, Wisconsin, and the Associated Charities in Milwaukee. In 1913, she became a deputy at the Wisconsin Industrial Commission and conducted surveys for the state's new minimum wage legislation.
In November 1914, Lundberg moved to Washington, D.C. to serve as the first Director of the Social Services Division of the United States Children's Bureau, a young agency established two years earlier. Shortly thereafter Katherine F. Lenroot, Lundberg's assistant at the Wisconsin Industrial Commission, also joined the Bureau and became the Assistant Director of the division. Lundberg directed studies on illegitimacy, juvenile delinquency, the care of children described then as mentally deficient and state child welfare laws. She wrote numerous articles and reports, and many of her studies were published as Children's Bureau publications. Her publications from this period include Illegitimacy as a Child Welfare Problem (1920, 1922), Juvenile Courts at Work (1925), both co-authored with Lenroot, along with Children Deprived of Parental Care (1926), and Public Aid to Mothers with Dependent Children (1926).
In 1925, Lundberg resigned from the Children's Bureau to join the Child Welfare League of America (CWLA), a coalition of child welfare organizations that was established in New York in 1920. Lundberg first served as the Director of the Department of Institutional Care, and later as the Director of Studies and Surveys. Besides her book Child Dependency in the United States (1933), she frequently authored articles in the CWLA's publications. In the early years of the Great Depression, based on her two decades of experience in social work, Lundberg was appointed the Director of Research and Statistics at the New York Temporary Emergency Relief Administration under Governor Franklin Delano Roosevelt. She also worked as a consultant for other public agencies and conducted research for Philadelphia and Florida.
Lundberg rejoined the Children's Bureau in 1935 at the request of Katherine Lenroot who had been promoted to the third Chief of the Bureau in December 1934. From 1935 to 1942 Lundberg served as the Assistant Director of the Child Welfare Division, and from 1942 to 1945 as consultant in social services for children. The responsibilities of the Children's Bureau expanded significantly during the New Deal, and Lundberg's contributions included laying the foundation of children welfare provisions under the Social Security Act of 1937. She was also the Assistant Secretary to the 1940 White House Conference on Children in a Democracy.
In 1945, Lundberg retired from Washington due to ill health. She continued to write nevertheless, and published Unto the Least of These: Social Services for Children in 1947. After Lenroot's retirement in 1951 and until Lundberg's death in 1954, Lundberg and Lenroot shared a home in Hartsdale, New York.
Emma O. Lundberg died on November 17, 1954; she was 73 years old.
Scope and Content
Emma O. Lundberg is best known for her research and numerous writings about child welfare. The largest part of this collection dates from her service at the U.S. Children's Bureau (1914-1925, 1935-1945), and at the Child Welfare League of America and the New York Temporary Emergency Relief Administration from the mid-1920s to the mid-1930s. A few materials from her pre-Washington years in Wisconsin are also present. Throughout the course of her career, Lundberg directed a number of studies about child welfare, and wrote not only about her findings but also about research methods useful for the field. Most of the Papers comprise drafts and reprints of Lundberg's writings, and her research files. Some of the drafts are heavily annotated. Very little purely personal material is found in this collection.
Along with Lundberg's own writings and printed materials, this collection contains a small amount of printed material by other individuals and child welfare organizations, which Lundberg filed for her own reference: reprints, journals, pamphlets, and clippings. Some are accompanied by correspondence and Lundberg's comments. Also present is a small amount of correspondence with her publishers and friends.
The Papers also include correspondence that Katherine Lenroot, a former colleague and a close friend of Lundberg's, exchanged with Lundberg's publishers and relatives after her death.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Writing and Speeches, 1914-1962
Subseries I.1: Previously Bound Writings and Speeches, 1914-1946
Subseries I.2: Writings and Speeches, 1919-1949
Subseries I.3: Writings--Printed Materials, 1914-1943
Subseries I.4: General, 1920-1962
Series II: Subject Files, 1834-1946
Series III: Personal, 1938-1971
Subjects
Lenroon, Katharine F. (Katharine Frederica), 1891-1982; Lundberg, Emma O. (Emma Octavia); Child Welfare League of America; United States.--Children's Bureau.; White House Conference on Children in a Democracy (1939-1940: Washington, D.C.); Children--Legal status, laws, etc.; Child welfare.; Foster home care.; Illegitimate children.; Juvenile courts.; Mothers' pensions.; People with mental disabilities.; Social security.; Social work with children.; Women social workers.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Selected Related Material at Columbia
Katherine F. Lenroot Papers, 1909-1974 Columbia University, Rare Book & Manuscript Library.
Selected Related Material at other Repositories
Child Welfare League of America Records University of Minnesota Libraries. Social Welfare History Archives.
Records of the United States Children's Bureau, 1908-1969 (Record Group 102) National Archives and Records Administration.
- Series I: Writings and Speeches, 1914-1962
  The writings contained within the collection are both those of Lundberg and those by other individuals and organizations.
  - Subseries I.1: Previously Bound Writings and Speeches, 1914- 1946
    This subseries contains Lundberg's writings dating from her times in the Wisconsin Industrial Commission to her second service in the United States Children's Bureau. The material, bound thematically by Lundberg, was unbound for preservation during processing, but the original order of the material has been maintained. Each folder includes multiple pieces of writings, which vary from reprints, annotated drafts and manuscripts, to research notes. A few letters related to the writings can also be found. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by the original titles within the binders.
    - Child Welfare Research, 1914- 1943, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Community and the Child, 1930-1940, (2 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 3 to 4)
    - County Organizations, 1921-1943 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Dependency, Illegitimacy, Mother's Aid, 1918- 1946 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Dependent Children, 1920s-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Evolution of Public and Private Foster Care, Aid to Dependent Children in Their Own Homes, 1924-1940s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Historical White House Conference, Post-war Planning, 1920- 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Juvenile Courts, 1920-1943, (2 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 2)
  - Subseries I.2: Writings and Speeches, 1919- 1949
    The writings and speeches included in this subseries are primarily in draft form and were produced after Lundberg joined the Children's Bureau. Some drafts are accompanied by her source materials and notes. This subseries also includes source materials for Lundberg's unidentified book chapters. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by title.
    Please note that most of the studies that Lundberg conducted with the New York Temporary Emergency Relief Administration are included in Katherine F. Lenroot Papers, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Columbia University Library.
    - "Aid for Dependent Children in Their Own Homes," 1924 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Causes and Prevention of Child Dependency," Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Causes of Child Dependency"--Source Materials, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Causes of Delinquency in Mothers' Aid Families," Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Changes Reflected in Foster-Care Statistics," 1930s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - "Changing Institution Types," late 1920s (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - "Child Dependency: Causes and Prevention," 1920s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - "Child Deprived of His Birthright," 1920 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - "Child in the Rural Community," 1937 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - "Child Placing by Early Institutions," 1930s (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - "Child Welfare"
      - Social Work Year Book, " 1946 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Social Work Year Book--Reprint and Typescript, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Typescript, late 1940s (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - "Child Welfare in Alabama," 1931 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - "Child Welfare in a Changing World," Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Child Welfare Records and Reports, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Child Welfare Research and Statistics"--Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Child Welfare Services in Rural Areas," 1940s (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Child Welfare under the Social Security Act," 1935 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - "Community Program," 1920s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "Comparative Growth of Institutional and Family Home Care," 1910s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - "Counseling Service in a Day Care Program"--Reprint and Typescript, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - "County Children's Homes," 1924 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - "Day Nurseries," 1931 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "Deaf Children: Beginning of the Education of the Deaf," late 1920s (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - "Evolution of Public and Private Foster Care," late 1930s- 1940s (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Federal Government and Child Welfare," Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Foster Home Care for Dependent Children"--Unidentified Book Chapter--Typescript and Source Materials, 1924-1926 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - "Government in Social Work," 1935 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - "Illegitimate Mother as a Delinquency Problem," Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - "Importance of Family Case Treatment in Child Welfare Work," Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Institutions for Dependent Children," 1926 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - "Institution Standards," Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - "Institutions under Public Auspices," late 1920s- 1930s (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - "Legal and Social Protection"--Unidentified Book Chapter--Source Materials, Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 17 to 18)
    - "Local Public Welfare"--Typescript and Notes, late 1930s (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - "Mental Deficiency: A Community Program," 1920s (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - "Mothers' Aid"
      - Collier's Encyclopedia --Typescript 1931 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Memorandum, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Social Work Year Book --Typescript, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - "Mothers' Pensions"--Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences--Typescript, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - "Mothers' Pensions in Florida," 1933 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - "Neighborhood and Family Conditions the Basis of Child Welfare," late 1920s (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - "Outline for Analysis of Child-Placing," 1930s (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - "Physically Handicapped Child," 1930s (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - "Present Trend in Care of Dependent Children," late 1920s (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - "Prevention Is the First Law of Child Welfare," 1930s- 1940s (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "Principles of Legislation Providing Aid to Dependent Children," 1922 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Public Aid for Children in their Own Homes," 1924 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Social Research," late 1940s (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - "Social Services for Children," 1941 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "Soldiers' Orphans' Homes," 1939 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - "Square Deal for Children Born Out of Wedlock," 1919 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - "Standards of Child Placing," late 1920s- 1930s (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - "Suggested Outline for Group Studying Child Welfare Needs," 1930 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - "Summary of Results of Inquiry in Preparation for Round Table Discussion of Mothers' Aid," 1931 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - "Supplementary Care"--Unidentified Book Chapter--Source Materials, 1930- 1937, (2 Folders) (Box 4, Folder 11 to 12)
    - "Trends in the Care of Dependent Children," late 1920s (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - "Uniform Illegitimacy Act," 1923 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "Words and Their Ways in Social Welfare"--Reprint, Typescript, Hand-written Notes, Clippings, and Correspondence, 1945-1946 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Subseries I.3. Writings--Printed Materials, 1914- 1943
    This small subseries consists of published reports and articles by Lundberg. The materials are arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Case Recording, 1938-1941 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Children of Illegitimate Birth and Measures for Their Protection, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - "Child Welfare Services"--Social Work Year Book, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - "County as a Unit for an Organized Program of Child Caring and Protective Work," 1926 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - "County Organization for Child Care and Protection," 1922 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Day Care, 1942 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Juvenile Courts, 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Post-war Problems, 1943-1944 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "Progress in Mothers' Aid"--Social Service Review, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - "Progress towards Better Laws for the Protection of Children Born out of Wedlock," 1920 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Research by State Welfare Departments in the Field of Child Dependency," 1932 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - State Commissions for the Study and Revision of Child-Welfare Laws, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - "White House Conferences"--Social Work Year Book, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Wisconsin Industrial Commission, 1914- 1916 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Subseries I.4. General, 1920-1962
    Within this subseries are a small number of articles, bulletins, pamphlets, and reports by other individuals and organizations in the field of child welfare. The folders have been arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Abbott, Grace, 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - American Public Welfare Association, 1934 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Beisser, Paul T., 1935 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - California Bulletin, 1940 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Canadian Welfare, 1936-1944 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Carson College for Orphan Girls, 1921- 1923 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Carstens, Christian C., 1927 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Child Welfare League of America, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Hanna, Agnes K., 1941 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Johns Hopkins University, 1925-1926 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Lenroot, Katharine F., 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - New York State Conference on Social Work, 1937- 1940 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - New York State Department of Social Welfare, 1936- 1939 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Philadelphia Relief Study, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Public Administration Service, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Public Affairs Committee, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Survey, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Taussig, Frances, 1922 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - United States Children's Bureau, 1920- 1942 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Warner, Charles H., 1924 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Series II: Subject Files, 1834-1946
  This series consists of subject files labeled by Lundberg. The subject matters relate to various aspects of child welfare, and the series includes printed materials, clippings, and handwritten research notes. Many of the subject files concern various types of child welfare institutions and legislation, and the coordinated efforts of local, state, and federal institutions to assist children. A significant amount of material is regarding early child care institutions from nineteenth century.
  Also present in this series are materials related to several White House Conferences that Lundberg attended. In the 1940 conference, Lundberg served as the Assistant Secretary. Included are articles, clippings, correspondence, pamphlets, proceedings, and speeches associated with the conferences. The material is arranged alphabetically by the original titles of the folders.
  - Almshouse Care of Children, 1932- 1944 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Apprenticeship and Indenture, 1924 and Undated (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Beginnings of Social Services for Children, 1921- 1944 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Biographies
    - Abbott, Grace, 1934-1939 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Carstens, Christian C., 1939 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Lathrop, Julia, 1932-1946 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Murphy, John Prentice, 1924- 1936 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Child-Caring Agencies, 1931-1945 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Child-Caring Institutions, 1925- 1946 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Child Protection in England--Early History, 1924- 1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Child Protective Agencies, 1931- 1944 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Children in Almshouses, 1923-1938 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Community Council, 1939-1945 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Community Organization, 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Coordinating Councils, 1935-1940 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - County Studies--Alabama, Undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Day Nurseries, 1937-1940 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Deaf Children, 1923-1943 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Delinquent Children--Care of--Early History, 1852- 1924, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Dependency and Neglect Jurisdiction in the Juvenile Court, 1937- 1941 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Dependent, Neglected, and Delinquent Children-- Early Statutes, 1861-1899 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Federal Emergency Relief Agency--Data on Families with Dependent Children, 1930-1935 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Foster Care, 1920s (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Illinois Private Laws, Undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Institutions and Agencies--Early--Reports of, 1834- 1929
    - Early--Reports of, 1834-1929 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - For Dependent Children--Early, 1925-1944, (2 Folders) (Box 6, Folder 17 to 18)
    - Trends, 1899-1934 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Institutions for Dependent Children--Trends in, 1927- 1940 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Inventory of Community Resources, 1921- 1944 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Massachusetts Reports--Excerpts from, 1866- 1942 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - National Conference of Social Work, 1940s (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Poor Laws, 1930-1943 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Prevention of Child Dependency, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Probation, 1936-1940 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Public Relief in New York State, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - State Care, 1923-1943, (3 Folders) (Box 7, Folder 10 to 12)
  - State Institutions--Data Regarding, Undated (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - St. Louis Board of Children's Guardians, 1937 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Transfer of Parental Control, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Transfer of Parental Rights, 1925- 1940 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Trends in Institutional Growth, 1943 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Uniform Illegitimacy Act, 1921- 1923 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Visiting Teacher, 1921-1933 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - White House Conferences
    - 1909 Conference-- Conclusions of, 1909 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - 1919 Conference--Minimum Standards for Child Welfare, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - 1930 Conference
      - "Children's Charter," 1931 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Joint Committee on Statistics--Draft, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Objectives, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - White House Conference on Children in a Democracy
      - American Forum of the Air, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - "Children in a Democracy"--Survey Article, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Drafts--By Lundberg, circa 1940 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Program, 1939 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Recommendations, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 8)
      - "Social Services for Children"--Preliminary Statements of the United States Children's Bureau, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 9)
      - Summary of Reports of Section IV, circa 1940 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Series III: Personal, 1938 -1971
  This series holds a small amount of correspondence and personal materials. A few letters with Lundberg's friends and publishers are present. Other personal materials include notebooks of her favorite poems and quotations.
  This series also contains Lundberg's will, in which she designated Lenroot as the executor of her estate, and other material related to her death. Correspondence that Lenroot exchanged with Lundberg's publishers and relatives can be found in this series. This series is arranged alphabetically by subject. Correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Clipping-- Lundberg's Funeral, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence
    - Lenroot, Katherine
      - Enochs, Elisabeth, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Hollander, Claire, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 13)
      - Lundberg, Howard, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 14)
      - McDermaid, Clarence, 1954-1956 (Box 8, Folder 15)
      - Morlock, Maud, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - McDermaid, Clarence, 1954-1956 (Box 8, Folder 17)
      - Reprint of Unto the Least of These, 1955- 1971, (2 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 18 to 19)
      - Paulson, Eveline, 1960 (Box 8, Folder 20)
      - Trout, Wendell, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Lundberg, Emma
      - Columbia University Press, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 22)
      - D. Appleton Century Company--Publication of Unto the Least of These, 1947-1949 (Box 8, Folder 23)
      - Greeting Cards--With Lundberg's Poems, 1944- 1948 (Box 8, Folder 24)
      - Lenroot, Katharine, Undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
      - New England Home for Little Wanderers, 1948 (Box 8, Folder 26)
      - Russell Sage Foundation, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Photograph--Katherine Lenroot, Undated (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - Poems and Quotations--By Others--Notebooks and Handwritten Notes, Undated (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - Will, 1947 (Box 8, Folder 30)